[Music]
this film is part of rebel wisdoms
series the science and psychology of
polarization so Alex Evans used to be a
UK government adviser working on climate
change in other big policy areas until
he became quite disillusioned with the
lack of big inspiring stories behind
government policy so in 2017 he wrote
this best-selling book called the myth
gap all about how he needed to recapture
big inspiring stories of hope and
renewal then he went on a bit of a
journey over the last couple of years
and he's now launching the collective
psychology project all about the growth
in polarization and the need for a
deeper shift towards collective
psychology and that's the subject we
talked a lot about on this channel is
polarization and what we might do about
it
you may start start with something about
polarization or about politics but you
seem to end up in psychology this is
very much part of the story of how I
ended up working on this because then
after the myth gap I spent a year as a
campaign director at of ours the 47
million member global citizens movement
and part of my job that was running its
brexit campaign and my brief was pretty
clear it was fight for the UK to remain
in the EU but it was as I was doing that
that I developed these increasing
misgivings about you know well actually
if we have a second referendum on brexit
is that really going to heal this kind
of septic wound in our politics and then
I took a sabbatical for six months and
went to live in Jerusalem with my family
for that period and obviously the
political polarization there is even
more extreme and at one level that was
incredibly depressing and I could see
the kind of similarities with brexit or
with Trump's America I mean obviously
it's more extreme in Israel and
Palestine but nevertheless I felt like
it was on the same spectrum in some
sense but what was hopeful when I was
there was finding the work of a few
psychologists people like Gina Ross who
are arguing that really to understand
polarization there you can't divorce it
from its mental health context
particularly the fact that continuous
traumatic stress which is a bit like
post-traumatic stress
when it's not post when it's just an
everyday ongoing reality but of course
that catalyzes polarization because the
classic symptoms of continuous traumatic
stress are things like anxiety and type
of vigilance and especially other ring
kind of projecting everyone onto some
idealized shadowy other and when enough
individuals display these symptoms of
course they start to manifest
politically - and you know of course the
the other reality there is that people
live in this constant low-level state of
threat perception
I mean Israelis are constantly at some
level perceiving threats of terrorism or
of rocket attacks or even of invasion
and then Palestinians are constantly
perceiving the threat of arbitrary
arrests or of their house being the next
to be demolished or of just living in
kind of conditions of more or less total
surveillance so everyone's triggered all
of the time and then you know I mean at
another level you look at that and you
think well I can see how this plays out
in a kind of conflict zone like this but
actually is it really is it overreaching
a bit to say that this is also relevant
to brexit or to trump and of course I'm
not saying that you know most voters in
Britain or the States are traumatized in
the SIS trick'd medical sense but the
threat perception absolutely shows up
when you look at opinion polling of why
do people vote Trump one of the
strongest predictors for that was this
sense that the American Way of life is
threatened it was the same with leave
voters in the UK many of whom clear
majority of whom agreed like you know
Britain increasingly feels like a
foreign country and that makes me feel
uncomfortable
so there's threat perception on that
side and then of course as soon as
you've had the presidential election in
2016 or the brexit referendum all the
kind of liberal cosmopolitan
internationalist type people also wake
up feeling like they're living in a
foreign country and that makes them feel
very uncomfortable now you know how it
feels right most and so the threat
perception is contagious and this is the
big risk that it becomes a kind of self
amplifying feedback loop and so one of
the questions right at the heart of the
collective psychology project is well
how would we reverse the polarity of
that feedback loop so instead of you
know these kind of mutually reinforcing
threat perceptions across the political
spectrum we have a kind of mutual
reinforcing process of sort of healing
and coming back together to a sense of
empathy for each other and respect for
each other's experiences and how we
reach the values that we've got and so
on my only concern with that narrative
is that it can seem almost condescending
because you're sort of saying and when
we talk about these things when we talk
about trumple we talk about brexit as
being only a product of sort of fear it
can sound like more of the liberal elite
kind of thinking well we know better
than you what why you've done something
how do you avoid that in the narrative
around this kind of conversation well I
think I mean as I say I think the issue
of threat perception is by no means
confined to one side of the political
spectrum I think on the contrary it's
something that's sort of cropping up
here there and everywhere but I mean of
course you know you can look at for
instance membership to the European
Union and make a completely trenchant
critique of the EU on very solid
rational basis that has nothing to do
with threat perception or fear or
anything like that and I would as it
happens by a lot of that critique myself
as much about the EU that needs
reforming but I think when you look at
the state of our political debate and
how much kind of triggering there is and
how much just Heat and you know
projection there is in the discourse
there's something deeper going on here
as well and what would you say that
deepening is is it is it that do you
think it's tied to social media or why
do you think that the level of threat
perception is rising as high as it is
right now so I think I mean when you
look at drivers of political
polarization and I've just finished a
big study on this for any Y you the
literature out there tends to talk about
three baskets of issues and one is about
the political stuff people feel deeply
disaffected with political systems with
elites corruption and so on second you
have a basket of stuff that's to do with
economics and partly that's about social
mobility and unemployment and inequality
but especially it seems to me this issue
of perceived relative economic
deprivation that you feel you're doing
less well than other people or maybe
less well than you used to be doing and
then the third basket is all about
culture and
values and identity and that's where
issues like immigration which are
obviously very polarizing sit so there's
those three baskets but I think what's
maybe been less well explored is the
extent to which each of those three
baskets has this psychological substrate
this sort of place where those issues
out there in the world come in to our
mental environments and how we perceive
them and whether we perceive them as
threatening scary triggering etc and
this is not an area that's either well
explored all that we invest much as a
society in you know helping us to build
our capacities on I mean I saw a lot of
the Cambridge analytic a story when I
was working at advisin you know I think
it's such a fascinating lesson and how
this data company was essentially able
to weaponize our own anxieties against
us to use this combination of
psychological targeting and technology
in particular social media micro
targeting to kind of press our buttons
with a very high degree of precision and
prompt a critical mass of people to see
the world in them anarse terms just when
it really counted and thereby tipping
election and my takeaway from that is
that it turns out that democracy really
depends on having a citizenry that has a
capacity to manage its mental and
emotional states but then if you look at
you know is that something we teach in
schools no not really is that something
that we put significant resource into in
the health service no not really we're
actually pretty unsure whose job it is
to help us navigate those things that
are right at the cusp of inner and outer
and right at the cusp of the individual
and the collective I think that's
probably because historically this has
been what religions have been in charge
of and then as religiosity has declined
and as religion has retreated from
public life we sort of looked around
thinking well who's in charge of this
now and we're really not sure you talked
about the need to kind of build that
kind of capacity how do you think we
might do that right so actually I think
there's a lot of fascinating work
already happening out there one of the
things that the report talks about is
that there's these three transitions
that are really important for us to make
both individually and collectively and
the
first one is from this kind of
fight-or-flight mode through to having
enough self-awareness to choose how to
react to situations the second one is to
move from powerlessness which is
something that lots of people feel
whether it's at home or at work or in
their communities or especially in
politics towards a sense of agency of
being able to chart their own course in
life and to help shape the course of
society and then the third one is a
transition from disconnection and
especially loneliness through to a sense
of belonging and you know there's really
great work happening out there in each
of those three fields I mean on building
self-awareness look at meditation apps
like Carmel headspace look at
organizations like cure violence in
Chicago who are incredibly good at
identifying people who are at risk of
getting involved in gang violence and
then focusing mental health support on
them to help them kind of manage their
states and cool off instead of acting
out when they're triggered so these are
you know great examples this is stuff
you can teach and stuff you can learn or
if you'll want to look at you know
building capacity for people to feel a
sense of agency there's some great
trainings out there whether that's
trainings to help you have difficult
conversations or figure out your life
purpose or build a political movement
that wants to go and change the world
those trainings exist or on belonging I
mean there's incredible work being done
by people like the cares family or
participate or ecity who are both doing
really great on-the-ground work to build
social connections in places where
they've really afraid so that's the good
news that there are these really bright
spots and that this is stuff that we can
train and learn and get better at but
you know the bad news is that overall as
a society we invest very very little in
this stuff and there's a ton of need so
you know we're starting from a low base
but we have some sense of you know where
we need to go to and can you talk a
little bit about the journey that you've
come to to get to this point because I
know that you used to work you've been
an advisor for the government for many
years and what I understand is that
you've kind of realized that the
solutions to these problems needs to
come from a deep
level than were normally looking for
right so I spent a long time as a policy
wonk in various guises I spent most of
my 20s wishing I was Josh Lyman in the
West Wing and so I worked as a special
advisor for two British government
ministers worked in the UN Secretary
General's Office for lots of think tanks
and my whole kind of theory have changed
if you like all that time was that you
basically get the right evidence you put
it in front of the right policymakers
and then things will happen and I
started to realize increasingly I
suppose from about 2011 onwards that
that wasn't really true there was a
particularly disillusioning United
Nations process that I was part of which
I went into thinking this is my dream
job to get evidence in front of
policymakers and it was very dispiriting
and that sent me on this journey of
wondering well you know if evidence and
data and arguments don't change the
world and what does and the first kind
of big part of that story was that it's
storytelling that really changes the
world and that's something that I wrote
about in a book called the myth gap
which came out in 2017 and the book was
published just after the brexit
referendum and just after Trump's
victory and of course when you looked at
people like Trump or Nigel Faraj you
know these clearly weren't people who
cry and because of the quality of their
evidence base they were just incredible
storytellers with particularly this
knack for tapping into people's fears
and kind of activating and amplifying
those fears and so what the myth gap was
really about was a sense of that you
know people on the authoritarian
populist right are very good at telling
these deep stories that particularly tap
into the modern absence of myth these
kind of shared stories that talk about
where we are and how we got here and who
we are and so at the time I wrote the
myth gap I thought well this is straight
forward progressive people you know
liberals and activists and campaigners
need to be just as good at storytelling
and then will take on the populist and
will win but since then I've become much
more interested in just popular sorry
polarization itself is the problem that
you know actually if all we're doing is
creating more weapons for progressives
to fight conservatives with we're just
deep in
this rift in our politics and actually
that's the thing that we have to heal if
we want to move forward from where we
are now are you familiar with polyvagal
theory and the idea so we didn't
interview with Peter Levine recently who
work very closely with Steven Porges who
came up with the idea of polyvagal
theory and we're also very familiar with
this sort of more trauma based work from
our retreats and the personal growth
stuff and my sense is that this kind of
understanding about threat perception
about how we orient ourselves and
particularly what I think polyvagal
theory is really important is saying we
can either be in an exploratory
framework where we can accept new
information and we can make contact with
people or in a defensive framework and
when we're in those defensive framework
everything that's coming in feels like a
threat
right so I'm no kind of expert in
polyvagal theory but I think it's an
absolutely fascinating avenue of inquiry
and it makes sense to me and as more
generally does the work of people like
Peter Levine and identifying that you
know trauma is not just something that
lives in our heads that it has a
physiological reality it's very much
embedded and stored in the body so I
think you know this is one of the
strands that can really help us to
become better at managing our states to
kind of know when we're triggered into
fight-or-flight mode and take the time
to step back and trigger you know move
back into a more reflective conscious
frame of mind and again you know this is
absolutely critical stuff for 21st
century citizens to be able to do it
really matters for the health of our
politics and you worked within the
political machine so you've got kind of
an idea about where like how out there
is this kind of talk this kind of work
compared to where the political
conversation is now and how much hope do
you have because there is this sort of
sense at least in the UK of ever
decreasing circles I mean everyone's
running out of ideas and run it it just
feels like politics is running down
rapidly yeah what's the distance between
sort of the political machine and this
kind of conversation so I certainly
don't think mainstream political
discourse is here yet I mean one of the
ideas
at the heart of the report that we've
just produced is the idea that the inner
and outer crises that we see in the
world and inside us are two sides of the
same coin
so on the one hand you have this sort of
pile of crises out there in the world
like climate breakdown and hyper
inequality and mass extinction and so on
and then over here you've got this pile
of mental health crises like suicide and
self-harm and anxiety and depression and
addiction and so on and so on and what
I'm arguing in the report is that at the
moment you know these two sets of crises
are fueling each other we feel messed up
inside partly because we feel like the
world is messed up out there and when we
feel messed up inside when we're kind of
triggered we act out in ways that worsen
the state of the world so again it's
another example of a feedback loop now
you look at mainstream politics as it is
today or for that matter the kind of
campaigning that you get from big global
NGOs it only talks about the outer stuff
it's all about you know issues in the
world of out there and it's just silent
on the question of the states of mind of
the citizens who are voting or the
policymakers who are making the decision
it's sort of you know they're just
completely separate now the good news is
that I think certainly politics is
paying much more attention to mental
health issues so loneliness now has a
dedicated Minister in the UK for example
and you know mindfulness now has an
all-party group in the British
Parliament there are lots of
policymakers who meditate so there's
this you know just like the rest of
society people who work in politics have
been increasingly realizing that yes
mental health matters but what we're not
seeing is that synthesis of recognizing
that you know our mental health our
state of mind matter for the state of
the world and vice versa but I think
that's partly because this isn't an idea
that's really surfaced much until
recently and now it feels like a lot of
people are converging on to this
territory I mean I don't feel at all
like the collective psychology projects
the only player in this space I think a
ton of people are sort of converging on
this space which gives me a lot of
hope that feels like this is something
that's kind of right that's ready to you
know mature and take root in the world
and I think therefore like you know I
don't see this as like expecting massive
pushback from people who work in
politics on this stuff I think that it's
just a question that we have to figure
out how to start seeding it so it can
take root and sprout and do you sense
the right place to start it's politics
because I've I've kind of had this
thought as well with we we run personal
growth retrieves we've always been
interested in bringing that kind of
deeper dimension into what we're doing
and my sense is that the only way to
change it really is to start with
culture is to change the cultural
narrative around psychology around
personal growth around therapy around
all these topics because politics will
always play catch-up to to culture
rather than the other way around
like it's very I I can't really imagine
presenting something to a minister and
getting them to buy into it it sort of
seems that it has to come from from
culture more right I'm very much in the
same place as you
I mean I think if if you took this idea
which is all about kind of our state of
consciousness and how that creates the
conditions for things to arise
politically whether that's good things
or really bad things which is what we're
seeing a lot of at the moment you know
that's a very distributed grassroots II
collective sort of proposition and you
know it's not this kind of little
bite-sized thing that you can make into
a lobbying ask on politicians or that
kind of thing but I think that there's
also a question there of what do we mean
by politics if we just mean what happens
inside the Westminster village then yeah
this stuff is you know at the moment
quite far from that even if we interpret
politics as meaning kind of activism I
mean again it's like a relatively small
subset of people in the population who
would see themselves as activists and
there's a much bigger group of people
who see activists is like a different
sort of person to me so you know maybe
they're kind of troublemakers and so
part of our problem I think is that
we've regarded politics is something to
be delegated to politicians or to
activists but not something that you
know we as ordinary people to ourselves
whereas actually you know that's of
course what the idea of citizenship is
all about and that's why I'm very
interested in
you know the idea of what constitutes
21st century citizenship what skills
does the 21st century citizen need and
you know in particular what state
management capacity is what in a sense
of agency and belonging does that
citizen rely on in a in order to be able
to do politics healthily constructively
you know in a way that builds futures
that we actually want you talked about
the that there's a gap in society where
religion used to be and I remember I
read the myth gap when you brought it
out a couple of years ago and I thought
that was really a really really good way
of looking at okay what are the deep
what is the deep mythos that we're
missing what is the gap that religion
filled that we need to re yeah hi so
it's a really interesting one I think
there are lots of facets to the gap I
mean as you say the myth gap was very
much about the kind of deep collective
stories that religion used to provide
when still of course does provide but
you know not to the same extent not in
the sense of being universally shared
reference points in the way that they
would once have been in individual
societies so the story aspect is part of
it I think in the collective psychology
project it's a little less about the
stories and a bit more about if you like
the social services that religions are
historically provided so I think that
when you look at kind of putting tools
for building self-awareness out into the
world at their best what religions have
done is offered things like you know
meditation and prayer which are very
effective tried and tested tools for
managing your emotional state or if you
look at the question of how religions
have helped people to build agency I
mean until the mid 1960s so many big
transformational political movements
were rooted in communities of faith
whether that the abolition of slavery or
the American civil rights struggle in
the 50s and 60s you know or remember the
other example labor
well the labor party is another one but
there's another particular example that
I can't remember Oh
women's suffrage no cancellation of
third-world debt actually in
in the 1990s and the early 2000s again
very much rooted in faith communities so
again at their best religions have
really performed this role of kind of
putting tools for agency out there into
the world and in terms of belonging of
course religions have been all about
creating congregational spaces where
people feel like they can belong in
spite of their differences in spite of
their shortcomings so that's if you like
a separate set of things that religions
have historically done for us but you
know as with myth it's something that
turns out to be incredibly important for
our collective psychological health and
now we're looking around for you know
how to fill that gap so I think in a way
the myth gap was sort of you know just
the beginning the thin end of the wedge
in this exploration of what what we have
lost as religion has receded from public
life and from our own lives but I don't
mean that to imply that you know the
myth gap was an argument that we should
all go back to church anymore than the
collective psychology project is an
argument to say we need religion back
because there are real reasons and often
very good reasons why religious
observance has declined I mean people
are rightly ready to point to many of
the hypocrisy of religions and all the
instances where religion divides us
rather than bringing us together and the
many historical wrongs that have been
perpetrated by religions I'm not
araly dismissing any of this I'm making
a different argument which is more
functional to say okay well you know if
we have decided that religions are not
going to perform these roles someone
else needs to perform these roles and in
the collective psychology project one of
the arguments is that you know that the
answer to whose job this stuff is is all
of us this is what kind of be sold for
us by a small number of expert
practitioners who are going to go off
into a room and come back and you know
come out with a solution because all of
us already are practitioners of
collective psychology especially in an
age disconnected with social media and
all the rest of it so it really matches
them you think we're practitioners of
collective psychology in a conscious way
rather than an unconscious triggered
reactive way just kind of
venting our shadows in our psychological
gunk out there into public life in a
completely kind of unreflective
unconscious way mmm because yeah that
there's collective psychology and
there's the idea of sort of collective
shadow and that's something that that
we've talked about quite a lot on the
channel it's like for me both bricks and
Trump were about kind of this what I
call the liberal shadow this sort of
sense of where we're so open we're so
tolerant to all these people apart from
all these people over here like the
deplorable famously in America and
people in America and in the UK picked
up on that and just that that's what I
think was a huge fuel of both brexit and
Trump and what I don't see so much at
the moment is a lot of progressives
recognizing oh wow actually this is what
we provoked this and that seems to be a
really important part of this collective
psychology process I'd say yeah I
couldn't agree with you more David I
mean you look at the story of change UK
this kind of brief insurgent political
party in the UK which now appears to be
in its Twilight just a few months after
it was launched but it was very
frustrating to watch because on the one
hand it was supposed to be this kind of
you know standard bearer for the remain
cause but on the other hand there was
just no acknowledgement of the
real-world grievances and in justices
that helped create the political
conditions in which brexit could happen
and there was no display of listening
and one of the interesting things I have
been exploring in work I've done for New
York University over the last few months
about political polarization is from
looking at countries that have
experienced civil wars or other huge
transitions where there's been very high
risk in many cases realized of extreme
political polarization and there's a
rich library of experience from those
countries about the kinds of things that
can rebuild common ground and it's
things like apologies and making a real
show of listening and you know often
they're kind of this is something that
populist obviously understand very well
that the performative dimensions of
politics really matter
symbolic and the imagery and the stories
and again you know progressives are
often bad at this because they you know
just think well we've got the answer in
terms of data and that's all you need I
mean look at climate activists ten years
ago they just thought well we've got the
Intergovernmental Panel on Climate
Change it says we're right you know what
else is there to say and then of course
the tea party came and ran rings around
them in terms of storytelling and you
know that led to losing basically ten
years of progress on climate change
until they sort of realized they need to
come back with a moral story about
responsibility for the future then that
was what unlocked the Paris climate
summit so there are examples of
progressives learning this lesson the
hard way but when you look at brexit and
you know it's immensely frustrating to
see how little learning has been about
you know the grievances this came from
the necessity of listening a kind of
requirement for acknowledgement of the
harm that's been done you know to kind
of communities that have been forgotten
about and left behind and disrespect it
exactly as you say mm-hmm yeah because
this is I mean I'm asked the question
like this earlier in the interview but
this is also my sense my concern about
these conversations when I hear them
taking place among people looking at the
kind of collective psychology side of it
or the the psychological side what it
what it can drift into sometimes this
sense of that we understand we we the
liberal classes understand what went on
yes it was a protest and yes we
acknowledge it and then we can kind of
move on to to but without a real
acknowledgement of okay what was it
about our attitudes to more traditional
communities for example that provoked
the response that that came and I think
personally I understand why brexit and
Trump happened and in a way I can see it
as a positive thing because it's sort of
the it's it's okay your society cannot
become too fragmented and to pull the
part without some kind of healing that
needs to take place right and I think
that's one of the interesting things
about polarization the political
polarization is not necessarily bad it
can play this role of shining a light on
injustice is that
gone ignored for too long but it's only
helpful if it you know it's that shining
of a light then leads to a kind of
process of right let's now deal with
these in justices and grievances that
have been brought to light if that
doesn't happen of course the risk is the
pain of the American white working-class
the industrialization and all of those
sort of things right so and there's you
know profound pain and trauma and
heartbreak on both sides of the
political spectrum and it's important to
attend to those wounds they need sort of
to be you know erred if you like so yeah
I I agree with all of that I think it's
I mean I I think in the risk with
framing something as collective
psychology is it sounds or it could
sound like you're suggesting tea and
sympathy as an alternative to getting
serious about real world in justices
that need to be sorted out through hard
edge you know policy I'm the report
takes a lot of care not to fall into
that trap I mean that's why the stress
on agency as one of the three key
transitions and this isn't just agency
in the sense of having agency over your
own life this is very much about yeah we
need the capacity to organize whether
that's locally or nationally to write
the kinds of wrongs that have led to
this polarization and you know it comes
back to that idea of citizenship again I
think it's that you know if you think
that it's a false dichotomy between
inner and outer and that you know the
two interplay in all kinds of ways you
can't possibly solve it by only
attending to the inner it's
understanding that there are all these
feedback loops and that attending to the
inner can help to unlock change in the
outer as well where do you think the
most resistance to this message going to
come from that's a really good question
I mean I think of course there's a bunch
of politicians and people in the media
doing very well out of polarization and
have no particular interest in
rebuilding common ground or promoting
empathy and
you typically wherever there's extreme
polarization you find those people at
the extremes I mean my favorite
illustration of this is how I sama bin
Laden once observed at the time when the
Iraq war was at its height that it seems
as if al Qaeda and the White House are
on the same team shooting at the United
States own goal because you know
American policy in Iraq played so
perfectly into our Qaeda's objectives
despite the fact that it was being
driven by the kind of most extreme most
polarized people within the Republican
establishment in Washington and of
course that's exactly in a terrorism is
the object lesson in this it's designed
to trigger a fear-based response that
then widens the divide and increases
recruitment by extremists at both ends
of the spectrum and you know you're
straight back into that game of kind of
feedback loops and the sort of Center
unraveling and so yeah people who are
doing well out of polarization often for
extremely cynical reasons will be the
first to come out and you know take
potshots at this or anything else but
seeking to rebuild common ground but the
truth is that the scale of the
challenges that we face whether that's
climate breakdown or mass extinction or
the economic injustice is that building
up in the world around us these issues
are way too big to be dealt with by one
side beating the other side you know
you're gonna solve climate change with a
sense of common purpose that's shared
across the whole of society so we do
really depend on rebuilding common
ground in order to kind of navigate
these global crises confronting us at
this point so where do you hope what do
you hope the report will achieve and
where do you think we need to go next or
where do you hope we go next right so I
think in the most immediate term I hope
that the report will Kindle a sense of
community in asking these questions
because as I said earlier these are not
areas that are going to be solved for us
by expert practitioners so it matters
that we create more spaces where all of
us can hold these questions and we
definitely hope to be part of catalyzing
that
I think there's also a big set of
questions about mapping out what's
already out there in terms of resources
to help us build our collective
psychological capacities and also to
figure out what's already out there that
is harmful because you know we're
failing the first do no harm test in so
many contexts and so many ways so as
well as building community one of the
things we want to focus on at the
project is some mapping projects looking
at sectors like the UK campaigning
sector for example or places like we're
interested in running collective
psychology maps in Leeds and in Bristol
but to do these very participative
processes where we're engaging more
people and sort of observing what in
their space in their city or their
sector is working what's not working
where are there gaps where are there
synergies where are the things that they
could you know do with just a small
tweak to their existing model that
aren't being done at the moment so the
mapping work is a big focus for the next
six months but then beyond that I'm
really interested in what sort of
infrastructure we need to start making
small bets in this sector because this
is this is really embryonic work we have
no idea what's actually gonna fly what
are going to be the interventions that
can really have a transformational
impact and go to scale and we're at a
point therefore where you know if we
make ten little bets nine of them are
gonna fail and then maybe that last
tenth bet has the potential to win big
so although we have a couple of small
bets at the collective psychology
project we'd like to make I think the
larger question is how do we create
systems and platforms for lots of little
experiments many of them very
small-scale or very local and for making
sure we share the learning from those
experiments among a kind of involving
community of people who feel like they
are practitioners of collective
psychology so that when we fail we do it
quickly and we make sure that as many
people as possible have access to the
lessons from that failure and then you
know we can iterate quickly and start to
figure out what's going to work in this
space but you know we're starting from a
pretty low base and we have a lot of
work
to do cool Alex thank you great thanks
again for having me rebel wisdom is a
new sense making platform bringing
together the most rebellious and
inspiring thinkers from around the world
if you're enjoying our content then you
can help us make more by becoming a
subscriber which will give you access to
a load of exclusive films also you can
then join our group zoom calls to
discuss the ideas in the films and you
can send us ideas for questions for
upcoming interviews we're also looking
for talented people to help us out with
editing graphics music that kind of
thing and if you're a regular viewer
you'll know we talked a lot about the
value of embodying or actually living
out the ideas that we talked about so
that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon
you